<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ACT xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://formex.publications.europa.eu/schema/formex-06.02.3-20250123.xd" NNC="YES"><BIB.INSTANCE><DOCUMENT.REF FILE="L_202502162EN.doc.fmx.xml"><COLL>L</COLL><NO.DOC FORMAT="YN" TYPE="OJ"><COM>EU</COM><YEAR>2025</YEAR><NO.CURRENT>2162</NO.CURRENT></NO.DOC><LG.OJ>EN</LG.OJ><PAGE.FIRST>1</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><VOLUME.REF>01</VOLUME.REF></DOCUMENT.REF><DATE ISO="20251027">20251027</DATE><LG.DOC>EN</LG.DOC><NO.SEQ>0001</NO.SEQ><PAGE.FIRST>1</PAGE.FIRST><PAGE.SEQ>1</PAGE.SEQ><PAGE.LAST>9</PAGE.LAST><PAGE.TOTAL>9</PAGE.TOTAL><NO.DOC FORMAT="YN" TYPE="OJ"><COM>EU</COM><YEAR>2025</YEAR><NO.CURRENT>2162</NO.CURRENT></NO.DOC></BIB.INSTANCE><TITLE><TI><P><HT TYPE="UC">Commission Implementing Regulation</HT> (EU) 2025/2162</P><P>of <DATE ISO="20251027">27 October 2025</DATE></P><P>laying down rules for the application of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 of the European Parliament and the Council as regards the accreditation of conformity assessment bodies performing the assessment of qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services they provide, the conformity assessment report and the conformity assessment scheme</P></TI></TITLE><PREAMBLE><PREAMBLE.INIT>THE EUROPEAN COMMISSION,</PREAMBLE.INIT><GR.VISA><VISA>Having regard to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union,</VISA><VISA>Having regard to Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 of the European Parliament and of the Council of <DATE ISO="20140723">23 July 2014</DATE> on electronic identification and trust services for electronic transactions in the internal market and repealing Directive 1999/93/EC<NOTE NOTE.ID="E0001" NUMBERING="ARAB" NUMBERING.CONTINUED="YES" TYPE="FOOTNOTE"><P><REF.DOC.OJ COLL="L" DATE.PUB="20140828" NO.OJ="257" PAGE.FIRST="73">OJ L 257, 28.8.2014, p. 73</REF.DOC.OJ>, ELI: <LINK URI="http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2014/910/oj">http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2014/910/oj</LINK>.</P></NOTE>, and in particular Article 20(4) thereof,</VISA></GR.VISA><GR.CONSID><GR.CONSID.INIT>Whereas:</GR.CONSID.INIT><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(1)</NO.P><TXT>Pursuant to Articles 20(1) and 21(1) of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014, qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services they provide are to be audited by conformity assessment bodies. The resulting conformity assessment reports confirm whether the requirements laid down in that Regulation and in Article 21 of Directive (EU) 2022/2555 of the European Parliament and of the Council<NOTE NOTE.ID="E0002" NUMBERING="ARAB" NUMBERING.CONTINUED="YES" TYPE="FOOTNOTE"><P>Directive (EU) 2022/2555 of the European Parliament and of the Council of <DATE ISO="20221214">14 December 2022</DATE> on measures for a high common level of cybersecurity across the Union, amending Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 and Directive (EU) 2018/1972, and repealing Directive (EU) 2016/1148 (NIS 2 Directive) (<REF.DOC.OJ COLL="L" DATE.PUB="20221227" NO.OJ="333" PAGE.FIRST="80">OJ L 333, 27.12.2022, p. 80</REF.DOC.OJ>, ELI: <LINK URI="http://data.europa.eu/eli/dir/2022/2555/oj">http://data.europa.eu/eli/dir/2022/2555/oj</LINK>).</P></NOTE> are fulfilled. Consequently, it is necessary to establish a harmonised and robust framework for the accreditation of conformity assessment bodies, the conformity assessment schemes they implement, the conformity assessments they perform in accordance with those schemes, and the resulting conformity assessment reports.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(2)</NO.P><TXT>The accreditation of conformity assessment bodies assessing qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services they provide, the conformity assessment report and the conformity assessment scheme should meet the requirements laid down in this Regulation. Conformity assessment bodies may satisfy these requirements either independently, by utilising composite certification or by subcontracting to duly accredited entities.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(3)</NO.P><TXT>Conformity assessment bodies accredited for assessing qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services they provide as regards the issuance of qualified electronic attestations of attributes should be permitted to issue the conformity assessment report required by Article 45f(3) of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(4)</NO.P><TXT>To contribute to the transparency of the accreditation process, the accreditation certificate issued to a conformity assessment body in accordance with Article 5 of Regulation (EC) No 765/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council<NOTE NOTE.ID="E0003" NUMBERING="ARAB" NUMBERING.CONTINUED="YES" TYPE="FOOTNOTE"><P>Regulation (EC) No 765/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council of <DATE ISO="20080709">9 July 2008</DATE> setting out the requirements for accreditation and market surveillance relating to the marketing of products and repealing Regulation (EEC) No 339/93 (<REF.DOC.OJ COLL="L" DATE.PUB="20080813" NO.OJ="218" PAGE.FIRST="30">OJ L 218, 13.8.2008, p. 30</REF.DOC.OJ>, ELI: <LINK URI="http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2008/765/oj">http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2008/765/oj</LINK>).</P></NOTE>, should contain sufficient information to enable third parties to verify that the accredited conformity assessment body is authorised to conduct a conformity assessment under Regulation (EU) No 910/2014.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(5)</NO.P><TXT>To maintain the integrity and accuracy of accreditation certificates, national accreditation bodies should ensure that these certificates reflect up-to-date information.</TXT></NP></CONSID><?PAGE NO="2"?><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(6)</NO.P><TXT>To ensure the integrity of the accreditation process, the accreditation certificate issued to a conformity assessment body may be subject to suspension or withdrawal at any time for each qualified trust service that the conformity assessment body has been accredited to assess. Suspension or withdrawal may occur after sanctioning by the national accreditation body or voluntarily by the conformity assessment body itself.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(7)</NO.P><TXT>For the purpose of harmonisation of this accreditation framework, this Regulation should be based on established standards, which reflect established practices and which are widely recognised within the relevant sectors.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(8)</NO.P><TXT>To enhance transparency, conformity assessment bodies should make the certificates of conformity that they issue publicly available. The certificates of conformity confirm the positive certification decisions taken by the conformity assessment bodies. However, the qualified status is only granted to, or withdrawn from, the trust service provider and the trust services they provide, by the supervisory body.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(9)</NO.P><TXT>To assess the compliance of qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services they provide with Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 and with Article 21 of Directive (EU) 2022/2555, conformity assessment bodies should use a conformity assessment scheme. Conformity assessment bodies should apply standards as benchmarks to assess qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services they provide, taking into account the versions and adaptations to these standards set out in the service specific implementing acts based on Regulation (EU) No 910/2014. These standards should reflect established practices and be widely recognised within the relevant sectors.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(10)</NO.P><TXT>Conformity assessment schemes set out the rules and procedures to be used by conformity assessment bodies in their assessments of qualified trust service providers and of the qualified trust services that they provide. Such schemes are evaluated by national accreditation bodies against the requirements set out in this Regulation. The content of such schemes is subject to changes over time. To facilitate the application of successive versions of conformity assessment schemes, the accredited conformity assessment bodies should put in place a specific process to manage evolutions of a scheme for which they are accredited.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(11)</NO.P><TXT>To oversee the development and maintenance of the conformity assessment schemes, each conformity assessment scheme should be assigned a scheme owner. Conformity assessment bodies, governmental bodies or an authority, a trade association, a group of conformity assessment bodies, or any appropriate body or group of bodies could be a scheme owner and could be different from the conformity assessment body operating the scheme.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(12)</NO.P><TXT>To ensure the continuity of the provision of their services, the accreditation of conformity assessment bodies should remain valid for earlier versions of standards referenced in the conformity assessment scheme. In those instances, the conformity assessment bodies should refer to those earlier versions of the standards explicitly, including the year and version number.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(13)</NO.P><TXT>To enhance flexibility, national accreditation bodies should be permitted to offer flexible scope accreditation, enabling conformity assessment bodies, in specific circumstances, to include additional activities in their scope of accreditation without the need for an evaluation by the national accreditation body. When designing the flexible scope accreditation, national accreditation bodies will consider the accreditation of flexible scopes as set out by European cooperation for Accreditation, appointed in accordance with Regulation (EC) No 765/2008. Where national accreditation bodies allow conformity assessment bodies to make use of such flexible scope accreditation, they should indicate it in the accreditation certificate for transparency purposes. To enhance flexibility even where national accreditation bodies do not offer flexible scope accreditation, they should carefully consider, before re-evaluating the accredited conformity assessment body, the impact of the changes to the conformity assessment scheme for which that body has been accredited.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(14)</NO.P><TXT>To ensure reliability of the conformity assessment schemes, owners should ensure that their conformity assessment schemes do not allow positive certification decisions, or any certificate of conformity, to be issued where the conformity assessment leads to the identification of any non-conformity with the requirements of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014, or with Article 21 of Directive (EU) 2022/2555, with regard to qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust service they provide. Indeed, while conformity assessment reports could include non-conformities and potential remediation plans, no certificate of conformity or positive certification decision should be issued when non-conformities are identified.</TXT></NP></CONSID><?PAGE NO="3"?><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(15)</NO.P><TXT>To ensure transparency in their practices, scheme owners should make publicly available a summary of their conformity assessment schemes. The summary should contain a description of the set of rules and procedures followed for the assessment of the conformity of qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services they provide with the requirements laid down in Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 and with Article 21 of Directive (EU) 2022/2555.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(16)</NO.P><TXT>To support the quality, security and reliability of the qualified trust service provider’s activities, the conformity assessment report should identify, where appropriate, opportunities for improvement that could refine the manner in which the qualified trust service provider and the qualified trust services they provide meet the applicable requirements.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(17)</NO.P><TXT>To support transparency and to facilitate the verification by supervisory bodies that an assessed qualified trust service provider and the qualified trust services they provide meet the applicable requirements, the conformity assessment report should include certain minimum information. In particular, for the purpose of facilitating the identification of the service entries to be listed in the national trusted list in accordance with Article 22 of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014, where applicable, a detailed description of the public key infrastructure functional hierarchy, per type of qualified trust service, should be provided in the conformity assessment report.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(18)</NO.P><TXT>To support transparency and facilitate the verification and monitoring of accreditation of conformity assessment bodies in accordance with Regulation (EU) No 910/2014, national accreditation bodies should, where applicable, provide an history of the scope of accreditation, including the start and, where applicable, the end date of the accreditation for each qualified trust service.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(19)</NO.P><TXT>To ensure continuity of conformity assessment bodies that have already been accredited, and to support the transition to the rules laid down in this Regulation, conformity assessment bodies that are currently accredited under standard ETSI EN <FT TYPE="NUMBER">319403</FT> version 2.2.2, or an earlier version thereof, would not need to be re-accredited under Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 until <DATE ISO="20270517">17 May 2027</DATE>. After this date, the conformity assessment bodies should be evaluated by the national accreditation body against the requirements set out in this Regulation.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(20)</NO.P><TXT>The Commission regularly assesses new technologies, practices, standards or technical specifications. In accordance with Recital 75 of Regulation (EU) 2024/1183 of the European Parliament and of the Council<NOTE NOTE.ID="E0004" NUMBERING="ARAB" NUMBERING.CONTINUED="YES" TYPE="FOOTNOTE"><P>Regulation (EU) 2024/1183 of the European Parliament and of the Council of <DATE ISO="20240411">11 April 2024</DATE> amending Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 as regards establishing the European Digital Identity Framework (<REF.DOC COLL="L" CONTEXT="EUR-LEX" DATE.PUB="20240430" NO.DOC="1183" URI="http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2024/1183/oj">OJ L, 2024/1183, 30.4.2024, ELI: http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2024/1183/oj</REF.DOC>).</P></NOTE>, the Commission should review and update this Implementing Regulation, if necessary, to keep it in line with global developments, new technologies, standards or technical specifications and to follow the best practices on the internal market.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(21)</NO.P><TXT>Regulation (EU) 2016/679 of the European Parliament and of the Council<NOTE NOTE.ID="E0005" NUMBERING="ARAB" NUMBERING.CONTINUED="YES" TYPE="FOOTNOTE"><P>Regulation (EU) 2016/679 of the European Parliament and of the Council of <DATE ISO="20160427">27 April 2016</DATE> on the protection of natural persons with regard to the processing of personal data and on the free movement of such data, and repealing Directive 95/46/EC (General Data Protection Regulation) (<REF.DOC.OJ COLL="L" DATE.PUB="20160504" NO.OJ="119" PAGE.FIRST="1">OJ L 119, 4.5.2016, p. 1</REF.DOC.OJ>, ELI: <LINK URI="http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2016/679/oj">http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2016/679/oj</LINK>).</P></NOTE> and, where relevant, Directive 2002/58/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council<NOTE NOTE.ID="E0006" NUMBERING="ARAB" NUMBERING.CONTINUED="YES" TYPE="FOOTNOTE"><P>Directive 2002/58/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of <DATE ISO="20020712">12 July 2002</DATE> concerning the processing of personal data and the protection of privacy in the electronic communications sector (Directive on privacy and electronic communications) (<REF.DOC.OJ COLL="L" DATE.PUB="20020731" NO.OJ="201" PAGE.FIRST="37">OJ L 201, 31.7.2002, p. 37</REF.DOC.OJ>, ELI: <LINK URI="http://data.europa.eu/eli/dir/2002/58/oj">http://data.europa.eu/eli/dir/2002/58/oj</LINK>).</P></NOTE> apply to the personal data processing activities under this Regulation.</TXT></NP></CONSID><?PAGE NO="4"?><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(22)</NO.P><TXT>The European Data Protection Supervisor was consulted in accordance with Article 42(1) of Regulation (EU) 2018/1725 of the European Parliament and of the Council<NOTE NOTE.ID="E0007" NUMBERING="ARAB" NUMBERING.CONTINUED="YES" TYPE="FOOTNOTE"><P>Regulation (EU) 2018/1725 of the European Parliament and of the Council of <DATE ISO="20181023">23 October 2018</DATE> on the protection of natural persons with regard to the processing of personal data by the Union institutions, bodies, offices and agencies and on the free movement of such data, and repealing Regulation (EC) No 45/2001 and Decision No 1247/2002/EC (<REF.DOC.OJ COLL="L" DATE.PUB="20181121" NO.OJ="295" PAGE.FIRST="39">OJ L 295, 21.11.2018, p. 39</REF.DOC.OJ>, ELI: <LINK URI="http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2018/1725/oj">http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2018/1725/oj</LINK>).</P></NOTE> and delivered its opinion on <DATE ISO="20250808">8 August 2025</DATE><NOTE NOTE.ID="E0008" NUMBERING="ARAB" NUMBERING.CONTINUED="YES" TYPE="FOOTNOTE"><P><LINK URI="https://www.edps.europa.eu/data-protection/our-work/publications/formal-comments/2025-08-08-edps-regarding-accreditation-conformity-assessment-bodies-performing-assessment-qualified-trust-service-providers-and-qualified-trust_en">EDPS Formal comments on the draft regarding the accreditation of conformity assessment bodies performing the assessment of qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services they provide | European Data Protection Supervisor</LINK>.</P></NOTE>.</TXT></NP></CONSID><CONSID><NP><NO.P>(23)</NO.P><TXT>The measures provided for in this Regulation are in accordance with the opinion of the committee established by Article 48 of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014,</TXT></NP></CONSID></GR.CONSID><PREAMBLE.FINAL>HAS ADOPTED THIS REGULATION:</PREAMBLE.FINAL></PREAMBLE><ENACTING.TERMS><ARTICLE IDENTIFIER="001"><TI.ART>Article 1</TI.ART><STI.ART>Definitions</STI.ART><ALINEA><P>For the purpose of this Regulation, the following definitions shall apply:</P><LIST TYPE="ARAB"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(1)</NO.P><TXT><QUOT.START CODE="2018" ID="QS0001" REF.END="QE0001"/>scheme owner<QUOT.END CODE="2019" ID="QE0001" REF.START="QS0001"/> means an entity or a group of entities which is responsible for developing and maintaining a conformity assessment scheme;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(2)</NO.P><TXT><QUOT.START CODE="2018" ID="QS0002" REF.END="QE0002"/>certification decision<QUOT.END CODE="2019" ID="QE0002" REF.START="QS0002"/> means a certification decision, which follows a conformity assessment conducted by a conformity assessment body where that body positively or negatively confirms the conformity of a specific qualified trust service provider and the qualified trust service it provides with the requirements laid down in Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 and with Article 21 of Directive (EU) 2022/2555;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(3)</NO.P><TXT><QUOT.START CODE="2018" ID="QS0003" REF.END="QE0003"/>certificate of conformity<QUOT.END CODE="2019" ID="QE0003" REF.START="QS0003"/> means a document by which a conformity assessment body attests a certification decision that positively confirms that a specific qualified trust service provider and the qualified trust service it provides comply with the requirements laid down in Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 and with Article 21 of Directive (EU) 2022/2555;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(4)</NO.P><TXT><QUOT.START CODE="2018" ID="QS0004" REF.END="QE0004"/>conformity assessment scheme<QUOT.END CODE="2019" ID="QE0004" REF.START="QS0004"/> means a set of rules and procedures to be used by conformity assessment bodies for the purpose of the assessment of the conformity of qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services that they provide with the requirements laid down in Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 and with Article 21 of Directive (EU) 2022/2555;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(5)</NO.P><TXT><QUOT.START CODE="2018" ID="QS0005" REF.END="QE0005"/>conformity assessment report<QUOT.END CODE="2019" ID="QE0005" REF.START="QS0005"/> means a document that provides detailed information, where applicable supplementary to that contained in a certification decision and associated certificate of conformity, on the method used to carry out, in accordance with a conformity assessment scheme, a conformity assessment of the compliance of a specific qualified trust service provider and the qualified trust service it provides with the requirements of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 and of Article 21 of Directive (EU) 2022/2555 and on the results of the conformity assessment;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(6)</NO.P><TXT><QUOT.START CODE="2018" ID="QS0006" REF.END="QE0006"/>accreditation<QUOT.END CODE="2019" ID="QE0006" REF.START="QS0006"/> means an accreditation, as defined in Article 2, point 10 of Regulation (EC) No 765/2008;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(7)</NO.P><TXT><QUOT.START CODE="2018" ID="QS0007" REF.END="QE0007"/>flexible scope accreditation<QUOT.END CODE="2019" ID="QE0007" REF.START="QS0007"/> means an accreditation where the specific conformity assessment activities for which accreditation is sought, or has been granted, are expressed to allow conformity assessment bodies to make changes in methodology and other parameters which fall within the competence of the conformity assessment body as confirmed by the national accreditation body;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(8)</NO.P><TXT><QUOT.START CODE="2018" ID="QS0008" REF.END="QE0008"/>national accreditation body<QUOT.END CODE="2019" ID="QE0008" REF.START="QS0008"/> means a national accreditation body as defined in Article 2, point 11, of Regulation (EC) No 765/2008.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></ALINEA></ARTICLE><?PAGE NO="5"?><ARTICLE IDENTIFIER="002"><TI.ART>Article 2</TI.ART><STI.ART>Accreditation of conformity assessment bodies</STI.ART><PARAG IDENTIFIER="002.001"><NO.PARAG>1.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>For the purposes of making certification decisions in accordance with a specific conformity assessment scheme, conformity assessment bodies shall be accredited in accordance with standard EN ISO/IEC 17065:2012 supplemented by standard ETSI EN <FT TYPE="NUMBER">319403</FT>-1 v2.3.1.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="002.002"><NO.PARAG>2.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>The accreditation of conformity assessment bodies referred to in paragraph 1 shall be performed by a national accreditation body in compliance with standard EN ISO/IEC 17011:2017.</ALINEA></PARAG></ARTICLE><ARTICLE IDENTIFIER="003"><TI.ART>Article 3</TI.ART><STI.ART>Accreditation certificate issued to conformity assessment bodies</STI.ART><PARAG IDENTIFIER="003.001"><NO.PARAG>1.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA><P>National accreditation bodies shall ensure that the accreditation certificates they issue to conformity assessment bodies contain at least the following information:</P><LIST TYPE="alpha"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>the unique accreditation certificate identity code;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>the issuance date of the accreditation certificate;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(c)</NO.P><TXT>the name and country, as stated in the national official records, of the national accreditation body issuing the accreditation certificate;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(d)</NO.P><TXT>the name and, where applicable, registration number as stated in the national official records, of the accredited conformity assessment body;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(e)</NO.P><TXT>the scope of accreditation, with regard to one or more of the following qualified trust services:</TXT><P><LIST TYPE="DASH"><ITEM><P>the issuance of qualified certificates for electronic signatures;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the issuance of qualified certificates for electronic seals;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the issuance of qualified certificates for website authentication;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the qualified validation service for qualified electronic signatures;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the qualified validation service for qualified electronic seals,</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the qualified preservation service for qualified electronic signatures;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the qualified preservation service for qualified electronic seals;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the creation of qualified electronic timestamps;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the provision of qualified electronic registered delivery services;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the qualified service for the management of remote qualified electronic signature creation devices;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the qualified service for the management of remote qualified electronic seal creation devices;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the provision of qualified electronic archiving services;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the issuance of qualified electronic attestations of attributes;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>the recording of electronic data in a qualified electronic ledger.</P></ITEM></LIST></P></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(f)</NO.P><TXT>the identification, including, where relevant, the specific version, of the conformity assessment scheme for which the conformity assessment body has been accredited;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(g)</NO.P><TXT>the indication of the use of the flexible scope accreditation, where relevant;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(h)</NO.P><TXT>the identification, where relevant, of the document outlining the design and implementation process of the flexible scope accreditation.</TXT></NP></ITEM></LIST></ALINEA></PARAG><?PAGE NO="6"?><PARAG IDENTIFIER="003.002"><NO.PARAG>2.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>National accreditation bodies shall ensure that the start date, and where applicable, the end date of the accreditation of the conformity assessment body for conducting the conformity assessment of the qualified trust services as referred to in paragraph 1, point (e), including specific dates for each qualified trust service as applicable, are part of the accreditation details referred to in Article 20(1b) of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="003.003"><NO.PARAG>3.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>National accreditation bodies shall ensure that any relevant changes made in relation to the information provided in accordance with paragraph 1 shall be clearly reflected in the accreditation certificate.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="003.004"><NO.PARAG>4.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>The accreditation certificate shall clearly describe the scope of the accreditation of the conformity assessment body, in accordance with Article 2(1).</ALINEA></PARAG></ARTICLE><ARTICLE IDENTIFIER="004"><TI.ART>Article 4</TI.ART><STI.ART>Reconsideration of existing accreditation</STI.ART><PARAG IDENTIFIER="004.001"><NO.PARAG>1.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>The scheme owner shall implement procedures to monitor any changes in the standards referred to in Article 2(1) or in Article 6(3), or to a conformity assessment scheme owned by it and on the basis of which a conformity assessment body has been accredited in accordance with Article 2.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="004.002"><NO.PARAG>2.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>The scheme owner shall notify the national accreditation body of the changes identified as a result of the procedures referred to in paragraph 1, in a timely manner.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="004.003"><NO.PARAG>3.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Where the national accreditation body did not apply flexible scope accreditation to accredited conformity assessment bodies, the national accreditation body shall determine whether the changes, identified as a result of the procedures referred to in paragraph 1, are likely to materially affect the ability of accredited conformity assessment bodies to conduct conformity assessments pursuant to schemes for which they have been accredited.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="004.004"><NO.PARAG>4.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Where the national accreditation body determines, pursuant to paragraph 3, that changes do affect the ability of conformity assessment bodies to conduct conformity assessments, it shall request the conformity assessment body to take appropriate measures within a reasonable prescribed period.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="004.005"><NO.PARAG>5.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>If the conformity assessment body is unable or unwilling to take the measures referred to in paragraph 4 within the period prescribed, the national accreditation body shall immediately withdraw or suspend the accreditation.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="004.006"><NO.PARAG>6.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Where the national accreditation body determines, pursuant to paragraph 3, that changes do not affect the ability of conformity assessment bodies to conduct conformity assessments, it may, where appropriate, extend the validity and scope of the accreditation of the assessed conformity assessment body.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="004.007"><NO.PARAG>7.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Where appropriate, the national accreditation body shall update the accreditation certificate in a timely manner to reflect the outcome of the reconsideration of the accreditation pursuant to this Article.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="004.008"><NO.PARAG>8.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Where a conformity assessment body receives a request pursuant to paragraph 4, it shall, in a timely manner, inform any qualified trust service providers that it has previously assessed under the relevant conformity assessment scheme of any impacts that the reconsideration of the conformity assessment body’s accreditation may have on those qualified trust service providers, including with respect to future certification decisions made by the conformity assessment body under that scheme.</ALINEA></PARAG></ARTICLE><ARTICLE IDENTIFIER="005"><TI.ART>Article 5</TI.ART><STI.ART>Conformity assessment bodies</STI.ART><PARAG IDENTIFIER="005.001"><NO.PARAG>1.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Conformity assessment bodies shall make the certificates of conformity they issue available in a public repository maintained by that conformity assessment body for that purpose.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="005.002"><NO.PARAG>2.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Any subcontracting by the conformity assessment body of the performance of conformity assessment activities shall duly consider the nature of the activity to be performed. The conformity assessment body shall ensure that the subcontractor complies with the standards set out in Annex I for the specific activity being subcontracted.</ALINEA></PARAG><?PAGE NO="7"?><PARAG IDENTIFIER="005.003"><NO.PARAG>3.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Conformity assessment bodies shall ensure, upon issuing a certification decision, that the qualified trust services provider to whom the decision relates, is able to submit the complete conformity assessment reports corresponding to that decision to the supervisory bodies.</ALINEA></PARAG></ARTICLE><ARTICLE IDENTIFIER="006"><TI.ART>Article 6</TI.ART><STI.ART>Conformity assessment schemes</STI.ART><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.001"><NO.PARAG>1.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Each conformity assessment scheme shall identify a scheme owner.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.002"><NO.PARAG>2.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>A conformity assessment scheme shall comply with scheme type 6 of standard EN ISO/IEC 17067:2013 and with the requirements laid down in this Article.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.003"><NO.PARAG>3.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Scheme owners shall ensure that their conformity assessment schemes include at least the standards, as applicable, set out in Annex II by indicating the year and version number of these standards.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.004"><NO.PARAG>4.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Scheme owners shall ensure that where a flexible scope accreditation is applicable, this is indicated in the conformity assessment scheme.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.005"><NO.PARAG>5.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA><P>Scheme owners shall ensure that their conformity assessment schemes establish processes and procedures, regarding at least the following:</P><LIST TYPE="alpha"><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(a)</NO.P><TXT>receiving and handling complaints to the scheme owner on the implementation of the conformity assessment scheme;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(b)</NO.P><TXT>notifications by the conformity assessment body to the supervisory body designated in accordance with Article 46b(1) of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 on the issuance of certificates of conformity and any changes thereto;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(c)</NO.P><TXT>where applicable, subcontracting the performance of conformity assessment activities by the conformity assessment body;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(d)</NO.P><TXT>the performance of yearly surveillance activities on the basis of the applicable requirements of clause 7.9 of standard ISO/IEC 17065:2012;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(e)</NO.P><TXT>the management and notification by the qualified trust service provider to the conformity assessment body and to the competent supervisory body of any change impacting the operation of qualified trust service providers or the qualified trust services they provide;</TXT></NP></ITEM><ITEM><NP><NO.P>(f)</NO.P><TXT>the verification of evidence demonstrating that the conformity assessment body:</TXT><P><LIST TYPE="DASH"><ITEM><P>has sufficient knowledge and expertise in the application of specific standards related to the qualified trust service provided by the qualified trust service provider, as referred to in paragraph 3;</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>has professional experience in conformity assessment in at least three assessments of trust service providers or three assessments of information security management systems; and</P></ITEM><ITEM><P>can ensure the availability of a team of no fewer than two qualified persons possessing the necessary expertise to carry out such conformity assessment.</P></ITEM></LIST></P></NP></ITEM></LIST></ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.006"><NO.PARAG>6.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Scheme owners shall ensure that their conformity assessment schemes require the qualified trust service providers to have processes, procedures and work instructions in place to notify the conformity assessment body at least one month before the qualified trust service providers implement any significant change in the provision of the qualified trust services certified under that scheme and at least three months before it intends to cease the provision of the services or parts thereof.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.007"><NO.PARAG>7.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Scheme owners shall ensure that their conformity assessment schemes do not allow positive certification decisions, or any certificate of conformity, to be issued where the conformity assessment leads to the identification of non-conformity of the assessed qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust service they provide with the requirements of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 and of Article 21 of Directive (EU) 2022/2555.</ALINEA></PARAG><?PAGE NO="8"?><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.008"><NO.PARAG>8.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Scheme owners shall ensure that their conformity assessment schemes set out the procedure for the attestation of a certificate of conformity. They shall require, in particular, that the qualified trust service providers immediately inform the competent supervisory body of any change to a certificate of conformity. They shall also require that qualified trust services providers refrain from providing the qualified trust services concerned or from advertising any reference thereto until the competent supervisory body reconfirms the qualified status. This procedure shall comply with the requirements set out in clause 7.11 of standard ISO/IEC 17065:2012.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.009"><NO.PARAG>9.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Scheme owners shall ensure that their conformity assessment schemes set out the conformity assessment process to be conducted over a sufficient number of person-days and shall ensure that sufficient resources and time are allocated for the conformity assessment, taking into account the scope and the complexity of the assessment.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.010"><NO.PARAG>10.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Scheme owners shall make a summary of the conformity assessment scheme publicly available for download. The summary shall contain a description of the set of rules and procedures followed for the assessment of the conformity of qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services they provide with the requirements of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 and of Article 21 of Directive (EU) 2022/2555.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="006.011"><NO.PARAG>11.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Scheme owners shall ensure that their conformity assessment schemes require that at least one surveillance conformity assessment is conducted annually for every evaluated qualified trust service.</ALINEA></PARAG></ARTICLE><ARTICLE IDENTIFIER="007"><TI.ART>Article 7</TI.ART><STI.ART>Conformity assessment reports</STI.ART><PARAG IDENTIFIER="007.001"><NO.PARAG>1.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>The conformity assessment report referred to in Article 20(1) of Regulation (EU) No 910/2014, shall comply with the specifications set out in Annex III.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="007.002"><NO.PARAG>2.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>The conformity assessment report shall be considered a part of the certification documentation specified in clause 7.7 of standard ETSI EN <FT TYPE="NUMBER">319403</FT>-1.</ALINEA></PARAG></ARTICLE><ARTICLE IDENTIFIER="008"><TI.ART>Article 8</TI.ART><STI.ART>Accreditation information</STI.ART><PARAG IDENTIFIER="008.001"><NO.PARAG>1.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Any interested party can request, free of charge, current and past information about the scope, start date and, where applicable, end date of the accreditation of conformity assessment bodies, for each type of qualified trust service that the conformity assessment body is or has been accredited to assess. This information shall be made available by national accreditation bodies.</ALINEA></PARAG><PARAG IDENTIFIER="008.002"><NO.PARAG>2.</NO.PARAG><ALINEA>Current and past information, as referred to in paragraph 1, should be made available for at least a period of 6 years after the accreditation of the conformity assessment body.</ALINEA></PARAG></ARTICLE><ARTICLE IDENTIFIER="009"><TI.ART>Article 9</TI.ART><STI.ART>Grandfathering provision</STI.ART><ALINEA>Conformity assessment bodies that have, before <DATE ISO="20251117">17 November 2025</DATE>, been accredited with reference to standard ETSI EN <FT TYPE="NUMBER">319403</FT> version 2.2.2, or earlier version, for the purposes of the assessment of conformity with Regulation (EU) No 910/2014 of qualified trust service providers and the qualified trust services they provide shall have their accreditation be considered to meet the requirements of Article 2(1) until <DATE ISO="20270517">17 May 2027</DATE>.</ALINEA></ARTICLE><?PAGE NO="9"?><ARTICLE IDENTIFIER="010"><TI.ART>Article 10</TI.ART><STI.ART>Entry into force</STI.ART><ALINEA>This Regulation shall enter into force on the twentieth day following that of its publication in the <HT TYPE="ITALIC">Official Journal of the European Union</HT>.</ALINEA></ARTICLE></ENACTING.TERMS><FINAL><P>This Regulation shall be binding in its entirety and directly applicable in all Member States.</P><SIGNATURE><PL.DATE><P>Done at Brussels, <DATE ISO="20251027">27 October 2025</DATE>.</P></PL.DATE><SIGNATORY><P><HT TYPE="ITALIC">For the Commission</HT></P><P><HT TYPE="ITALIC">The President</HT></P><P>Ursula <HT TYPE="UC">von der Leyen</HT></P></SIGNATORY></SIGNATURE></FINAL></ACT>
